In this video, we will be introduced to
Hooke's
law and how oscillations can happen in
springs.
Next video, we'll be further analyzing
this
through energy diagrams and how potential
energy
can alternate with kinetic energy.
But let's focus on this lesson first.
First
of all, let's say we have a spring and it
is stretched by a distance of x metres.
So if the spring was at rest, let's say it
would
look like this. Let's do it like that.
Now, when the spring is stretched by a
distance
of x, it's going to apply a force on the
object
that is attached to the string. And this
force
is called the restoring force. And it's
the
force applied on an object that tries to
make
the spring go back to equilibrium or its
resting
position. And equilibrium refers to that.
This force is given as
force is negative kx, where x is the
distance
travelled or the distance stretched by the
spring,
and k is the spring constant.
Since the force is a vector, we know it's
negative
because x, if it stretches in the positive
direction
over here, the force is going to be
applied
the other way. Now, k is the spring
constant,
and basically it's a numerical value of
how
stiff the spring is.
And usually k is given to you in these
types
of questions. If k is not given to you, if
it
doesn't ask you to solve k, you probably
won't
be needing this formula. Negative kx, I
kind
of rewrote that, but that's basically this
equation.
Now, the same thing can also happen when
the
spring is compressed. Let's say it's
compressed
by a distance of y now.
So we're going to put this down, and let's
call
this y. Now, let's try to draw a free-body
diagram
on this box. There is going to be gravity
and
normal force, fN, fG, where normal force
is
perpendicular to the surface, and also
there
is going to be the restoring force, fr.
Now, in a lot of these questions, when
it's
oscillating, there will not be friction.
But
if we say something like the box is going
to
be launched, then friction might be in
this
problem. So, if it's not moving, let's say
it's
released from rest, the initial type of
friction
will be static friction because it's not
moving,
so fstatic. However, if we're drawing the
free
body diagram while it's in motion, which a
lot
of the times we have to do because we have
to
calculate kinematics, then we would be
using
the kinetic friction and using the kinetic
friction
coefficient. And that's basically the
forces
exerted on this box, or this object.
Now, energy continuously changes form, and
we're
going to learn that in the next video.
For a mass-spring system, though, we know
that
for a pendulum, the period is 2 pi root L
over
G. In this case, it's quite the same
thing,
but with a bit of variable changes. So the
period
of a spring is equal to 2 pi root M over
k. So, as you notice, there are some
differences
between this new period and the previous
period.
Now, this period depends on the mass of
the
object. A heavier object would have a
larger
time for it to oscillate because the
period
would be larger. And the stiffness, or the
spring
constant, is also a factor that comes into
play
for a period. And you could also notice
that
period doesn't depend on amplitude.
So, in real systems, friction and air
resistance
are present. Otherwise, when you pull a
spring,
it's just going to keep on going until a
net
external force is applied to it, Newton's
law.
So, this basically causes oscillations
that
have an amplitude that decreases over
time,
and that's called damped oscillations.
And this is present in every experimental
or every real-life case, where basically
amplitude
decreases over time due to friction
and air resistance. And
it's present in real life.
And over time, if damping is large enough,
this
will stop oscillations completely. So, the
two
formulas we learned today that will
probably
be given on your formula sheet if you're
doing
IB or AP are T of a spring is 2 pi root m
over
k, and the restoring force, or the force
of
a spring, is equal to negative spring
constant
and x, where k is the spring constant or
the
stiffness, and x is the distance
displaced.
Next video, we will be looking at some
examples
of this, and we are going to be
introducing
how we can relate energy to equilibrium,
because
if you think about it, when you oscillate
it,
at this point, there is going to be
potential
energy at max, but at the middle, when
it's
at equilibrium and it's still going this
way,
kinetic energy is at max, which means it's
the
fastest at equilibrium when you oscillate
it.
And we will be looking into that, and I'll
be
explaining that more in depth in the next
video.
So, thank you for listening, and I hope
you
enjoyed this video. Bye!